SAGARMOY SENGUPTA

9739158424 • sagarmoysengupta@gmail.com • Kormangala, Bengaluru, Karnataka, 560037, India • Open to Relocate • LinkedIn • X (10K Followers) • Github • Blog

Staff Software Engineer

Backend lead with a decade of software and technology architecture experience. Led a 10-member team to develop a petabyte-scale data processing platform for major corporations, resulting in successful project completion. Skilled in Project Management , FullStack Development and Cloud Architecture on AWS and GCP. Mentored over 20+ engineer on best practices for building distributed systems and code quality. Talk to 10,000+ software engineers on Twitter by simplifying complex computer science concepts.

Professional Experience

Periscope by Mckinsey, India Staff Software Engineer, Bengaluru

Apr 2023 - Present

- Led a team of 10 developers at Periscope, overseeing the development and roadmap creation for a petabyte-scale data processing platform, enabling pricing strategy optimization for major corporations like Coca-Cola and Walmart.
- Managed projects by implementing collaborative and open culture to celebrate innovations and failures resulting in a 2x boost in developer productivity while consistently achieving delivery timelines.
- Provided technical mentorship to junior team members, imparting best practices for developing scalable distributed systems and fostering autonomy within the team, resulting in an increase of code quality by 30% and a decrease in bugs by 20%
- Collaborated with principal engineers and product leads to align technical designs with product requirements during the development of a highly-scalable microservice backend using Go, AWS services like ECS for containerization, Aurora MySQL for databases along with Terraform configuration management.
- Implemented Infrastructure as Code (IAC) using Terraform for automating the deployment of AWS resources, resulting in a 30% reduction in provisioning time and enhanced security through consistent resource configurations.

Lowes, India Dec 2020 - Mar 2023

Lead Software Engineer, Bengaluru

- Led the design and implementation of scalable MicroServices architecture on Google Cloud Platform using Docker and K8S, catering to over 150M Active Users
- Collaborated closely with product leads to ensure that technical designs aligned seamlessly with product requirements from planning phase through monitoring progress for effective project management.
- Led the development Loyalty platform, resulting in a 40% increase in user engagement and \$3bn of additional revenue to the company
- Led the enhancement of DevOps deployment tactics resulting in a significant 50% improvement in development cycle efficiency; documented over 30 High-Level Designs (HLDs) and Architectural Decision Records (ADRs), aligning the team towards customer first approach.
- Mentored junior engineers within the team providing guidance on technological responsibilities while fostering autonomy and driving initiatives that enhanced code quality standards across products contributing to an overall improvement of product reliability by 30%.

General Electric Aviation, India Software Engineer, Bangalore

Nov 2018 - Nov 2020

- Led the development of a highly-scalable backend flight engine software utilizing FSA to track over 50,000 operational aircraft worldwide, contributing to the safety and maintenance efficiency of critical aviation systems.
- Led a team of 4 engineers to develop and deliver data pipelines, infrastructure, and frontend systems using Angular, NodeJS, and Python on AWS, ensuring the successful handling of over 3PB of data.

Siemens, India Nov 2017 - Nov 2018

Software Developer, Bangalore

• Contributed to the design and architecture of Siemens DCS+ Order Management System augmenting its modifiability by 25%, meeting all quality requirements set forth alongside ensuring adherence to coding standards leading to increased code quality across the backend system.

Accenture, India Nov 2014 - Nov 2017

• Learned, built and deployed software applications for various industries using various technologies but mostly Angular JS, Java and SQL Server

Core Competencies

Programming Languages Python (Programming Language), GoLang, TypeScript, JavaScript (Programming Language) **Cloud Platforms** Amazon Web Services, Google Cloud Platform (GCP)

Web Development Angular (Web Framework), ReactJS, NextJS, Flask, Django

DevOps and Containers Kubernetes, Docker (Software), DevOps, Jenkins, YAML

Database Management MongoDB, PostgreSQL, DynamoDB

Awards

High Performer Award for Leading Lowes Loyalty Program, Lowe's

Innovations Award, Siemens

Jan 2001

Apex Performer Award, Accenture

Jan 2001

Ace Award, Accenture

Jan 2001

Education

West Bengal University of Technology, Kolkata , India, Computer Science and Engineering in Bachelor of Technology, Jul 2010 - Jun 2014